<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The baterie of the Popes Botereulx, commonly called the high altare. Compiled by W.S. in the yere of oure Lorde. 1550</title>
            <author>Salesbury, William, 1520?-1600?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104718</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4959</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11355)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4959)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 145:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The baterie of the Popes Botereulx, commonly called the high altare. Compiled by W.S. in the yere of oure Lorde. 1550</title>
                  <author>Salesbury, William, 1520?-1600?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[108] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [R. Grafton for] Robert Crowley, dwellyng in Elye tentes in Holburne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The yere of our Lord. M.D.L. [1550]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.S. = William Salesbury.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication and publisher's name from colophon; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G(-G7-8).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:1"/>
            <p>The baterie of the Popes Botereulx, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye called the high Altare. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by W. S. in the yere of oure Lorde. 1550.</p>
            <bibl>ii. Cor. x.</bibl>
            <p>The wapons of our war are not fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but mighty before God to caſt downe ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g holdes, wherwyth we ouerthrowe ymaginacions, and euerye hygh thynge that exalteth it ſelfe agaynſt the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and bringe in captiuitie al vnderſtanding to the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſte and are ready to take ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geaunce on all diſobedience, when your obedience is fulfilled.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶To hys ſinguler good Lord, ſyr Richarde Ryche, Lorde Ryche, &amp; Lord Chauncelloure of Englande: his mooſte fayethfull and humble ſeruaunte Wyllyam Saleſburye wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth euerlaſtynge feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as I can not refrayn but diſcloſe and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it, ſo can I not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyly expreſſe or declare, howe ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe a thing it is to our eares, how confortable to our herte, and howe pleaſant to our eyes, to hear, vnder ſtande, and ſe: that your lordſhyppe (hauynge ſuch power geuen you of God and your Prince to ſuppreſſe, beate downe, and vtterly aboliſh, al vayne ſuperſticion and falſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as you haue) doeth nowe, by the abundaunte grace of almighty God workinge in your hert, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repugne, ſuppres, &amp; beate downe thoſe vayne ceremonies, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiouſe
<pb facs="tcp:4959:3"/>
obſeruaunces founded by the Byſhoppe of Rome, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ye haue (to the moſte part of men) bene thought to fauoure, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and maintaine.</p>
            <p>In very dede. Theſe manifeſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens that do nowe appeare in your good Lordeſhyp, are verye ioyous vnto all ſuche men, as delite to ſe al ſuperſtition aboliſhed, and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſet forth and maintened: but much more ioyous to me and ſuche other, as be towarde your lordſhip in ſeruice. For nowe (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked therfore) we haue aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye inoughe wherewyth to ſtoppe the mouthes of the euil ſpeakers, ſo that if they wyll not otherwyſe be anſwered, we maye ſaye as Chriſt dyd to the froward Iewes. Operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus credite. Lette the worckes (whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ye ſe openlye done) cauſe you to leaue of your euyll ſpeakyng, and to
<pb facs="tcp:4959:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
learne to ſpeake wel of ſuch as god hath ſet in authoritie.</p>
            <p>And to declare myne opinion of your Lordſhippe, I haue thought it my dutye (beynge moued in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to write agaynſt the deuiliſh abuſe of altares, ſo ſtifelie maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ſtifenecked Papiſtes) to dedicate the ſame mi labours vnto youre good Lordeſhyppe, truſting that if you will voucheſalfe to ſette it forthe vnder your name, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will with better will embrace it and be the more edified by it.</p>
            <p>Wyth full truſte therefore, that your Lordeſhyp will be my bucke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and ſhylde of defence, whylſe I fyghte vnder the banner of the lord of Hoſtes: I haue couragiouſelye geuen the onſet vpon the Romiſhe Enemyes, bendynge myne ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce againſt the ſtrong &amp; mighty Botereulx of their Bulwarke (the
<pb facs="tcp:4959:4"/>
hygh altare I meane) whyche bei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng ſhaken downe, I doubt not the forte wyll ſone be yelded vnto my grande capitaine Ieſu Chriſte. Who preſerue your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to his honoure, &amp; your lordſhips euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting wealth. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>William Saleſburye to the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as muche (good chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reader) as ſince the fyrſte begynninge of the deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the Popes Lawes in Englande, and ſynce the firſte ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion &amp; ſeueringe of hys vayne ſuperſticyons frome Chryſtes true religion here among vs, I haue not lyghtly ſene the leaſte toye, the moſt folyſhe fantaſye, nor the moſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frutefull ceremonye, forbidden and taken away bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly maieſtrates wythout much detraction, &amp; backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitinge of ſuche papyſtes as had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie learnyng, nor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſecret mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muracion, and ofte ſtumblynge of the vnlerned &amp; ſymple people, who are nothynge ſo ſoore to be blamed therefore, as the learned and crafty Papiſtes, whiche will neyther (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the Phariſeis) receiue the worde
<pb facs="tcp:4959:5"/>
of God theim ſelues, nor yet ſuffer other to do it. Therfore haue I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies not onely deteſted the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne maner of the one ſorte, lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge the miſerable ſtate of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but alſo dyd euer miſdread the verification of the Prognoſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to truly calculed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid papiſtes vnder the meridia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their Romiſhe proceadinges. But now bicauſe I wold (in as much as in me mayly) put to my helpyng ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to falſifie or rather to preuent al ſuch inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and miſchiues (as now bi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to happen of the vntaught, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, of the ſimple people) I haue here made a rude, and a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple litle boke, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the rude &amp; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people, that (as I haue now ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nified before) they beynge the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perſwaded bi manifeſtes textes of holye ſcripture, ſhal not haue the
<pb facs="tcp:4959:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
like occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to murmure to grudge or to be offended, neither wyth the godlye proceadynges of the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Metropolitane of Englande (who as redoubted gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d captaine hath fyrſt enterpriſed on this moſte notable feact) nor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any other by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or lawfull officer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> attemteth the lyke affaires: that is,<note place="margin">Alluſio ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſis e ticolai Nepiſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pi Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nienſium</note> to plucke down &amp; remoue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſh alters out of Chriſtes churches or temples.</p>
            <p>And moreouer bicauſe I perceiued (as one of the beſt lerned papiſtical doctors in England gaue me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by defending his aultares, and that with toth and nayle &amp; fumiſhe fearcenes, rather with the auctoritie of wreſted Scryptures) and was full perſwaded that all the learnede papiſtes will ſtyflye continue in the mayntenaunce of their hallowed aulters: therefore was I conſtrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd lytle boke more
<pb facs="tcp:4959:6"/>
pithy and ſubſtauncial and ſo more diffuſe and harder to be vnderſtand then I wyllingly had intended.</p>
            <p>Wherfore who ſo euer wyll vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, let him reade it thorowlye and if he therby get any more lyght or perfect knowledge in the matter intreated, let him thanke and prayſe God the grauntor therof. To whom be all honour and glorye. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶The baterye of the Popes Botereulx.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is a poynt of infamye in a valeant warry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to ſteale on his enymyes ere they be ware, or to go aboute to entrappe them, and haue them at a vauntage, vnleſſe he do fyrſte gyue them a notable warnyng, eyther by the thunderinge of a bombarde, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the bounchynge on a drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlade, eyther by ſcrikinge of a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, eyther els by ſome other coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſſe alarme, noyſe, or ſhoutynge, whereby hys audacitie, hardynes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of victorie, myght ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be inſituated vnto his enemies than crafty wyles, ſely cowardnes and diſtruſte of hauynge the vpper hande: ſo myne enemyes peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:4959:7"/>
wold impute vnto me the lyke in glory &amp; reproch, if I do not admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of my propoſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict in beſieging their Botereulx. Forth auoidinge wherof (and for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in no wyſe I may be faynt or falſe harted, as longe as I war vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dert blaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the gioriouſe armes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe Lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trybe of Iehuda) let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfor take this for a warning pece y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now I inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d furthw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> war is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed betwixt vs lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ago) to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, bet down, &amp; araſe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oldma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but an other like for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres of the old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s making, for the onli defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his made god: whych fortres y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts cal an alter: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god the ſacrament of the alter. But they might as wel &amp; as anagogicalli cal their alter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tower, &amp; their houeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge god ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged therouer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hauke of the
<pb facs="tcp:4959:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
tower. But as I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gyue their god no propre name: (ſo at this time for the pariforme, proporcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſituatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it I wil name their alter a Botere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ulx, which if we by might of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord of hoſts ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bater down to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the popes church ſhal greatly ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derouſly wauer, and their god euer houer.</p>
            <p>Nowe therfore ye Papiſtes take hede to your Botereulx, for now I go in hand to charge my baterynge pieces, and ſay not but that I giue you warnyng that neyther the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worne puiſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> douty captain Moſes, who was ſo mightye for a time, nor yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your erth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, the glitteringe of his triple crown, ne yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuring charecters croſewiſe graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be a ſufficiente fortification for to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your ſayd Botereulx: No though ye cluſter &amp; daube it rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> woll, clods
<pb facs="tcp:4959:8"/>
turfes, erth, mire, dyrt, &amp; ſuch triſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traſhe: no no though ye pray in aide the greate Turke, the Soulden the Sophy &amp; al the Saracens, yea and though al the hereticall ſectes of the whole world came to you and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe on your ſyde all the wicked ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that their high general Sathan ſhall ſuggerate into theire braynes. Take hede therfor yet ne left y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your Botereulx haue not a ſtedfaſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion: For if we can proue that it be founded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moſes and not on Chryſt: than was it deſtroyed in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte. M.D.lxxvii. yere a goo.</p>
            <p>But fyrſt or we go about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licion of this Botereulx, bi the good dylygence of maſter Grammer the chiefe vndermyner, we wyll ſearche what foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is of: and bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt Botereulx or altare was v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongeſt the Hebrues: we wyl ſee what was the primatiue name
<pb facs="tcp:4959:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that they gaue it (for thereby wee may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thruſt open one win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow) for truly thei according to the veri vſe therof, in their holy la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gage, named y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alter Midhſbach, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the ſacrary or the place to offre vp ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice on. The prieſt, the offycer or the doer therof, thei called medhſa beach The ſacrifice or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offeryng they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it Dhſebach. So lykewiſe the grace of the Greke tong ſhal declare vnto them the ſelf nature of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vocables &amp; that by the help of theſe words: <hi>Thyſiaſterio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Thyſcos</hi> or <hi>Thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, Thyſia.</hi> Which words a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not lightly expreſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lyke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnitie nother in latyn nor Engliſh except a man wold ſpeake on this wyſe, Sacrariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſacrificus, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſacrari, ſacraficer, ſacrifice. And than do we take this word ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crarye for an altare, whiche worde altare and none other, all Nacions
<pb facs="tcp:4959:9"/>
that receiued the faith at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the ſee of Rome: do vſurpe ſtil in this ſignificacion. Neuertheles ye do now perceiue bi the Etimology and true expoſition of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue ſaid Hebrue and greke words: that thei be ſo nighe of kinne in betokening, and ſo like in ſpeakinge in thoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, as be theſe thre wordes in Engliſhe: Houſe, huſbande, &amp; huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye can not wel denye but that they be ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iugate, yoked, and knitte togither, as well in ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication as in ſyllabication, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth one of them can not be ſeuered from an other: nor the nature of one of theym canne be declared wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out makynge mencion of the other: nor one can be aboliſhed, forbidden or deſtroyed: excepte the other two be abolyſhed, forbidden &amp; diſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo. Therefore may you gather that we do not greatly ſtray frome
<pb facs="tcp:4959:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our hygh way, at what time ſo euer we ſpeke of ſacrificer, or of ſacrifice beſyde this terme Altare.</p>
            <p>Now therfore O thou Lorde of Hooſtes, make my face to preuayle agaynſt all lyinge braggers faces: and harden thou my forhed agaynſt their forheades: ſo that my forhead be harder than an adamant or flynt ſtone, that I may be leſſe afrayde of them. O thou moſt myghtie Lorde Iah, defend me againſt the cankred malyce and wycked pollecye of the Popes ſoldiours, who (I dare wel ſaye) wyl not onelye ſtand ſtyflye in defence of theyr popyſh fortres, but with a terrible countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce bi gnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing their tethe togyther wyl ſtep forth, vibrate and ſhake their veny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous dartes towardes me threte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng me after thys ſorte. Thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exerciſed tyron, thou freſh water ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyoure: thou yongeman I ſaye: da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſte
<pb facs="tcp:4959:10"/>
thou approch vs? dareſt thou aſſault vs? dareſte thou once adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to aſſiege oure inuincible for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe? Yea, or thinkeſt thou it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any gunne ſhote to broſe the weakeſſe part of the wals, which continued ſo manye. M. yeares vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſaulted, vnuiolated, &amp; vntouched? whoſe mortare is waxen as harde as the flint ſtone, whoſe ſtones are as hard as ſtele, &amp; whoſe timbre is as toughe &amp; as durable as it were of fyr tre. Recule therfore my good ſonne recule. But bycauſe we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the to be ſo deſperate a felow that thou wilt ſance remedy, other ſinke or ſwymme, and either take a fal or giue a fal, &amp; ether hab or nab, we thinke it beſte for vs (leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture thi captain come w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter force vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we loke for) to make our ſelues in a redines to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our holye altare which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſte
<pb facs="tcp:4959:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Botereulx, yea this Botereulx ſhall not paſſe on thy baterye (but god forgiue me to miſname ſo holy a thynge) but nowe I perceiue the olde ſayde ſawe to be to true. <hi>Qui taug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t picem, comquinabitur ab ea.</hi> I will ſay no more, but good inough.</p>
            <p>And nowe not to diſſemble, ye are a ſtarcke heritike, in that you do fantaſy to haue our altares throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe in al churches. But thys is a wonderful matter, that we muſt be faine to proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the holy churche of Rome had neuer in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but let vs alone w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this matter, &amp; wolde god we could proue our tranſubſtanciation, oure purgatory fyre, our popes primacy &amp; other like matters of no leſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as wel &amp; as euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tli as we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue this.<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the papiſtes in wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng the ſcripturs</note> For we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue how our altares had their beginning .ii. M. &amp; odde .C. yeres paſſed, as any
<pb facs="tcp:4959:11"/>
Chriſten man that liſteth may reade Geneſis capitulo octauo. How the holye Patriarke Noe, after that he had come oute of the Arke, buylded an altare to the lord and toke of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cleane beaſte, and of euerye cleane foule, and offred ſacrifices in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. And the lorde ſmelled a ſwete ſauour: And the Lorde ſayd in hys herte: I wyll not procede to curſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground any more for mans ſake, for the imaginacion of mannes herte is euell from his youth &amp;c. And Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham likewiſe builded an altare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lord euen in that place where he had appeared vnto hym and dyd call on the name of the Lorde. And Iacob alſo beyng commaunded of the Lord and bycauſe he had heard hym in the daye of hys tribulacyon, buylded an altare vnto the Lorde: and called the place the God of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell: bycauſe that God had apeared
<pb facs="tcp:4959:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto him there, when he fled frome he face of his brother. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And farther ye ſhal reade how that God after that he had yeuen the ten Commaundementes, by the hande of Moſes commaunded alſo thus. An altare of earth thou ſhalt make vnto me, and theron offre thy burnt offringes, and thy peace offringes, thi ſhepe and thine oxen in al places where I ſhal put the in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my name, thithir wil I come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the, and bleſſe the. Item. Exodi. xxix. Seuen dayes (ſayth the lorde) thou ſhalt reconcile vpon the altare &amp; ſanctify it, &amp; it ſhal be an altermoſt holy. Exo. xxx. And y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt make an altare to burne ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Of Sethim woode ſhalt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> make it, a cubit lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; a cubite bredth: euen fowre ſquare ſhall it be, and .ii. cubites hye. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Item .iii. Reg. xviii. The holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Elias vtterly to bringe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb facs="tcp:4959:12"/>
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe God Baall &amp; his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes &amp; to ſet furth the glory of the liuynge God: toke xii. ſtones accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the numbre of the twelue Tribes of the Sonnes of Iacob, &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtones he made an altare, in the name of the lord &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We could alledge .vi. hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bible beſide theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we now recited, which ſhold ſtyl make on oure parte if nede requyred, but bicauſe they are ſo comenly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wyl at this time ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe them: for we truſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue alredy brought auctorities inough to proue the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cientie, the laudabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual acteptau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of alters before almighti God in the old law. But now to proue the confirmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them bi the new law ye ſhal read theſe other textes. But firſt marcke well how that Chryſt himſelfe ſayd Mat. v. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> offreſt thy gift at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, and ther remembreſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:4959:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath ought againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>: leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine offringe before the altare, and go thy way firſte and be reconciled to thy brother, and then come &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy gyft. Lo ye may ſe here how the altare is twyſe ſpoken of, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> where the reaſon conſyſteth but of very few wordes. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſhal reade of this word altare in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxiii. chapt. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Euangeliſt, wher Chriſt himſelfe alſo ſayth: from the bloud of the rightouſe Abel, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of zacharias the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of Barachias whom ye ſlew betwen the temple &amp; the altare, Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lu. i. Ther appered vnto zacharias an Angel of the lord ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ſide of the altare, of ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Act. xvii. As I paſſed bi (ſaith. ſ. Paule) &amp; beheld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner how ye worſhip your gods, I fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d an alter wherin was writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to the vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god. And again, the holy Apoſtell Paule to putte vs herein oute of all doubtes, ſayeth:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:13"/>Do not you knowe howe that they which miniſter about holy thinges lyue of the ſacrifice? and they why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wayte on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alter, are partakers of the alter?</p>
            <p>More ouer in the ſixte chapter of the Apocalipſis ye ſhal reade of an altare to.</p>
            <p>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had opened the fifth ſeale (ſayth Iohn) I ſaw vnder the altare the ſoules of them that were killed for the worde of god, and for the teſtimonye whiche they had. &amp;c. And in the eyght chapter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Apocalipſis, you ſhall reade of thre altares, and ſo nighe togither, that they fall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of thre lines almoſte, and one of them beynge a golden altare. &amp;c. Item Apoca. xi.</p>
            <p>Than was geuen me a reed (ſayth thys holy Euaungeliſt) like vnto a rodde, and an angel ſtode and ſaid. Ryſe and meaſure the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God
<pb facs="tcp:4959:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and the altare, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that worſhyp therin: and the quyre that is within the temple. &amp;c. Lo ſyr, here ye maye playnelye reade in the verye texte of a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, of an altare, &amp; of a quyre to, &amp; yet theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the new learning, wyl nether haue temple, altare, nor quyre, or at the leaſte wayes if they muſte haue a temple, they by their wyl, woulde haue it to be without quyre, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute altare, without ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and without any maner of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, veſtimentes, and dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynges. Yea, they wold haue it like a barne, or like a mannes dwelling houſe, hauynge neyther reſpecte to the faſhyon of the tabernacles, nor the temples of the Hebrues, nether to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the church of Rome</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, that lefte vs in the holye wryte ſuche manifeſte teſtimonyes as wee haue nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, whereby we maye eaſilye
<pb facs="tcp:4959:14"/>
confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all ſuch naughty heritikes as wil preſume to talk againſt our laudable ceremonies, or any other decent things which haue bene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to be had in our temples and haue continued amonge all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſince Chriſt was borne, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeres before, as I haue already declared by ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry textes of the ſcripture, as well of the new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde. And beſide all thys we might ratifye the ſame by diuerſe places of our Canon lawe, vnles it were now abrogated, &amp; by thauctoriti of very auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doctors For doth not the holy doctour. S. Auguſtine. Li. xxi. cap. x. <hi>De ciui. dei</hi> (ſpeaking of the infideles) wryght thus. They vnto their gods haue builded te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples alſo, &amp; haue ſet vp al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, &amp; haue offred ſacrifices. Now bicauſe theſe felowes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t away w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lerning of old catholike doctours, we wil cite
<pb facs="tcp:4959:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
no more of their work: But ſhal we not be as blameles as .ſ. Paule to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in for our purpoſe ſuch places of noble Poets, as may be thought co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient. For as I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre Ouid in a certaine place of hys worckes writeth much after this ſence.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Whan Medea was come home, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the dores ſhe ſtode,</p>
               <p>Vſynge no mannes companye, whyle ſhe was in that mode.</p>
               <p>Twey alters tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſoddes ſhe made, and garniſhed with bowes:</p>
               <p>And a blacke Kamme ſhe Sacrificed, to twey greate Goddaſes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Ye may read alſo in the chiefeſte Poete amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Latines, as thus.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Firſte with theſe thre thru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of thre hewes, I the enuiron do,</p>
               <p>And rounde aboute theſe altares eke, wyth thyne image I go.</p>
            </q>
            <p>But bicauſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now a daies giue no credite in a maner to poetry and not very much to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde fathers we wil allege no mo places of them nother: truſting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al good catholike people wil be eſtabliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:4959:15"/>
by theſe ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t proues which are brought hitherto, &amp; ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alters haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed &amp; had in ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>digne reuerence euer ſince Noes floude (&amp; who is it that can tell the contrarye but that Cain and Abel the ſonnes of Adam offred their oblacions vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altares?) And wher al maner of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thorowe out the wide worlde (were they neuer ſo ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in true knowledge) ether by the inſtinction of the Lawe of Nature printed by Gods fyngere in their hertes, ether by imitacion of Gods owne electe people, the Hebrues thought it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expedyent and no leſſe neceſſarye to buylde them altares whereupon they myght offre theire ſacrifices to worſhip, pacifie, and gratifie theyre Gods wythall. Without which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares as moſt agreable inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts euery man knoweth no ſacryfce can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye offred or orderly fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted.
<pb facs="tcp:4959:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Wherfore let al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the good and holſom conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of the holy churche of Rome: herken, embrace and cleaue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that mainteigne altares as thinges moſt neceſſary and moſt feteſt to mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter the ſacrament of the altare v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon: in which ſacrament for a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (as ſayeth. ſ. Auguſtine) al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men offre vp them ſelues in the ſelfe ſame offring, which the church doth celebrate. Ergo to conclude of the whole ſumme of all the prymiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, altares muſt nedes be had in al churches to miniſter the ſacrament of the alter vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now therfore he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce fourthe let vs haue no more ado a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this mater, for ye ſe how plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly how largely and howe trulye we haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paines to diſcuſſe it: yea &amp; I warrant you that this ergo ſhall greue to the guttes (if they ſo eſcap) all thoſe altary heretikes ſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:16"/>
bragger which wold ſo faine bater oure Botereulx (as he termeth it) nay I wara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you we haue batered him out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way: wher art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> I ſay y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> baterer of our Botereulx? where art thou? yt is to the that we ſpeke? No?<note place="margin">The Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>umph be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the victory.</note> not as muche as one woorde? why tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mum bouget, and we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent. Heih let vs be of good chere, our fortreſſe ſhall not yet downe.</p>
            <p>And if youre fortreſſe ſhall not yet downe, I tell you, I the ſelfe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you thought you had nowe of late ſlayne or at the leſt wayſe put to ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, it is euen he that telleth you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn that your fortreſſe ſhall down if not yet, yet ſhortli. And it ſhal not only be throwen downe, but it ſhal be arraced &amp; made eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> handſmothe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For now I haue you by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> back, I haue ſpied, al your ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cour, all your refuge, all your pore pieces, your diſordered ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4959:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
your harmeles harneys. For youre pieces are ſo pore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhortly you ſhal not drinke a halfe penyworth of ale by them: your ordinaunce are ſo diſordered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei are liker to deſtroy your owne men than others: &amp; your harneys are ſo harmeles that their werers ſome hornwode or dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the head piece lieth caſt down &amp; troaden: the gauntletes are worne on the fete, the ſappodines on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, the collar on the ancles, the va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces on the legges: the greues on the armes: &amp; all the reſt are no righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter placed. Neyther wyll I denaye but that all your armoure be verye ſtrong of them ſelues, of the ryght makynge, and of greate force if ye coulde welde them: but bicauſe you haue ſtolen them oute of oure Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn his armory, and entend alſo ſo vnſhamefaſtly to abuſe them agein his honour and magnyfycence they
<pb facs="tcp:4959:17"/>
ſhal ſtande you in no ſtede (&amp; howe can they, ſeynge ye can not rightlye vſe them?) whan ye ſhall haue moſt nede of them.</p>
            <p>But nowe to put on our armour that we maye immediatlye go tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this oure begon combate, and to ſpeake more playnely. Al the teſtimonyes that you broughte on your behalfe oute of the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, are as true, as nothynge is more true: neyther (as I ſignifyed before) do I doubte anye thinge of the trueth of them: and I thinke no leſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other textes which you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged out of the newe teſtamente.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles I am not ſo dull, ſo farre ſeduced, nor ſo void of al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtandynge, but that I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue howe craftely, and howe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly ye go about by your long reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of all the ſayde textes, to blinde and caſt duſte in the eyes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned
<pb facs="tcp:4959:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſymple people, who haue not that capacitie that they (by comparynge together the olde law &amp; the new) can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehend how to ſeuer the one frome the other, or to knowe in what point y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yth or diſagreeth wyth the other, or howe to accord them togyther: for they both are one in effecte, though diuerſly ſet forth. They both tend to one ende: but the one is conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mate and ended, the other endureth to the laſte daye.</p>
            <p>Neither is it any wonder at all, if the vnlearned people, or the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally learned attaine not the deſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to examine the exacte differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwene the lawe and the Goſpell, or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not iuſtely diſcuſſe after what ſort the lawe is abrogated, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what ſort the obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lawe is damnable in a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea it is no wonder I ſaye, though the
<pb facs="tcp:4959:18"/>
worldlye wiſe manne can not right lye iudge in ſuch diuine matters, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that ſome of the holy apoſtles were in the ſame takinge, whiles it pleaſed the gloriouſſe maieſtye of GOD as it were to wythdrawe his Spirite frome them (therefore good Lord do not thou put vs out of thy preſence, neither take awaye thy holye Spirite frome vs) for what cauſed Peter and Iames to attribute ouer muche vnto the law of Moſes, but that they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted (for that while) of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God: which Spirit neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode (I meane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually) vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye man ſauing on chriſt only.</p>
            <p>And what made ſo manye vaine ceremonies and damnable ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticions as well oute of the Lawe of Moſes as out of Hethens rites to crepe into Chriſtes religion, but bycauſe that the ſpirite of GOD
<pb facs="tcp:4959:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hadde departed frome the maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thereof, and for that the pure goſpell ne was not diſcretely ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Moſes his lawe, nor wel purged of the Heathen and infidels their folyſhe traditions? As for an exemple. To praye and our faces turned eaſtwarde, to faſte theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bringe dayes, haue we taken of the Heathen, or infideles.</p>
            <p>And to truſte that we do a good dede in reſtinge and ceaſſinge onely frome bodilye laboure and excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, on Sondayes or Holye dayes and not rather to the entente that we might giue our ſelues wholy to reſte and ceaſe to worcke or excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe oure owne carnall worckes, and to heare the worde of GOD preached, occupiynge oure ſelues in prayers and meditation to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:19"/>Such vngodly idle reſt &amp; mock ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly day, haue we ſucked oute of the dug of Moſes law, &amp; to offer bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſacrifices, is to be fathered v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſame Moſes, &amp; not vpon Ieſus Chriſte: whyche miſfathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge hath filled Chriſtes churche with ſo many popyſhe altares, as we ſhal anon begin to declare more particulerly, according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or gyfte whych we receiued of Chriſt. But bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> altares were made but for Sacrifices ſake, we ſhal fyrſt ſpeke ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what of ſacrifices</p>
            <p>And in as muche as this worde ſacrifice is but a borowed terme in Englyſhe, and therefore the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation therof not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ſhal ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the vnlearned what is mente by ſacrifice.<note place="margin">What ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice is</note> Sacrifice is an offering vp of our work, which we exhibite to God, whom we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be ſuche one, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely
<pb facs="tcp:4959:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
we ought to preſent this our ſeruice or worſhyppe vnto. Which ſeruice, worſhip, or reuerence (as is afore ſayd) is naturallye planted in the hertes of all men, as well of the Heathen as of the Iewes, of the learned as of the vnlearned: &amp; euen in the hertes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that neuer heard of god, which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g cauſeth ſuch as haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true knowlege of gods word (as it were childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bi making of babes, or the like trifeling imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) to inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry kindes of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing or worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they take for god. All which ſacrifices &amp; worſhipping being inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corrupt &amp; ſinfull nature of man, &amp; not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on true faieth, is no better eſtemed for acceptable worſhip before god, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> babe or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pupet of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childs maki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be a perfite workema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iugme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a ſeuere &amp; a ſage old fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:4959:20"/>
And therfore (me thynketh) it is no leſſe folli for vs, who profeſſe Chriſtes doctrine to learne of the Heathen people (to whom the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of the euangelye is not reuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) any poynte of religion, then if prudente princes, learned lawiers, honeſte huſbande men, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulte wyth infantes or chyldren of two or thre yere of age, how to rule their Realmes, pleade their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges, or to huſbande their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrye. For it is to euident as wel bi prophane as holi ſcripture, how the Heathen nations dyd not onely ſwarue from the true worſhipinge of god, but dyd greuouſly diſpleaſe hys diuine maieſtye. And thoughe God ſhewed him ſelf vnto them by the worcke of the Creation of the worlde, yet they haue not prayſed nor thanked hym accordinglye, but became vayne in their imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:4959:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and their folyſhe hertes were blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Whan they counted them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues wyſe, they became foles: and turned the glory of the incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble god, into the image of a corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tible man, and of byrdes, and four foted, and of creping beaſtes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore god likewiſe gaue them vp vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to their hertes luſte, into vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which turned the truth of god into a lye, and worſhipped and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the creature more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, whych is bleſſed for euer. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore god gaue them vp vnto ſhamefull luſtes. For their women chaunged the naturall luſtes into the vnnaturall: lykewyſe the men alſo left y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natural vſe of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in their luſts one on another, &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man wroughte filthines, &amp; receiued in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues the reward of their erroure, as it was according. And as thei regarded not to knowe
<pb facs="tcp:4959:21"/>
God, euen ſo God delyuered them vppe vnto a leude mynde, that they ſhoulde do thoſe thynges whyche were not comely, beynge full of all vnrighteouſnes, fornicacyon, wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, couetouſnes, maliciouſnes full of enuye, murther, debate, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, euel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicioned, whiſperers, backbyters, haters of god, diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, proude, boaſters, bryngers vp of euell thinges, diſobediente to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, without vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t breakers, vnlouinge truce breakers, vnmercifull.</p>
            <p>Whiche men though they knew the righteouſnes of God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered not how that they which committe ſuch thynges, are worthy of death, not only they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do the ſame, but alſo they which haue pleaſure in them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do them. And fathermore beſyde all this miſcheuous abſurditie that S. Paule declared by them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:4959:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
imaginacion of theire corrupte nature beyng not regenerate of the ſpirite of God did ſo far co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to nature it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſa. cvi. Leui. xx.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei kylled men yea their owne begotten chyldrene and ſacrificed them not to God nor yet to the creatures of god, but euen to verye deuyls. And if you (I meane you altare pryeſtes) do delyght to learne the Heathens maner of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficynge, recorde well theſe verſes in your mynde.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Et capita inferno et,<note place="margin">A memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> patri tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite lumen.</p>
               <p>Geue heads to Pluto the God infernal. And Saturne his father, the fire iuſtral.</p>
            </q>
            <p>But how hydeouſe, how terrible &amp; howe deueliſh a thing it is for any Chriſtian to folowe any ſuch mens rites or ceremonies: I leaue to the iudgment of any godlye man.</p>
            <p>Neyther wyll I denye but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Heathen had altares amongeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but onely inuented, made, and occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pied
<pb facs="tcp:4959:22"/>
for no better purpoſe, than is nowe before ſayd: whyche is to ſaye, to offer vp Sacrifices vnto Deuelis.</p>
            <p>And as many ſo euer as lyſte to offer vp ſacrifices vnto Deuilis: they maye full well grownde theyr procedyngs vpon the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, &amp; ſo builde as many altares as ſhall pleaſe them and mayntane the ſame as longe as they may.</p>
            <p>But nowe to returne to the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Iews. The Iews had diuers ſacrifices or ſortes of offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges (whoſe names in the Hebrue tonge I wyl nowe omitte, for thes Englyſh printars are ſo thryfty as to haue neuer an Hebrue letter to printe wythal.</p>
            <p>But I wyll name theym as they be communely englyſhed, that is: Peace offerynge, Synne offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge, Meate offeryng, Drincke
<pb facs="tcp:4959:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
offeryng, Waue offerynge, Heaue offerynge.</p>
            <p>All whych ſacrifices or offerings are comprehendyd in theſe two names: Pacifiyng Sacrifice, and Gratifiyng Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of the Pacifiynge Sacrifice,<note place="margin">Thocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the pacifiyng ſacrifice.</note> was the laps or fall of our forefather Adam, by whoſe fal all mankynde halteth, hoppeth and walloweth in the dyrty Puddle of ſynne, lyith cheyned wyth the Iron cheynes of Gods Wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce, taken Captyues of the Prynce of thys world, and become Enimies and Rebelles agaynſte the God of myght.</p>
            <p>For whoſe preſumptuouſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſturdy Rebellion, it lay in no mans powre to make a loue-daye bytwene God and man, nor paye ſo greate a raunſome as was iuſtly to be demaundyd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:23"/>Therfore if man wold recouer hys old fall, go an vpright gate agayne, aryſe vp oute of the fyllthye puddle of ſynne, be releaſed of the vntolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable cheynes of Gods wrath and vengeaunce, and be deliuered out of the captiuite of the deuel, &amp; brought agayne into the amytie, fauour and frendſhyp of God: than by al iuſtice it behoued him to pacify the ire and indignacion of God with as full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction and with as dewe and as plentiful compenſacyon as ſhoulde counteruayle the tranſgreſſyon and diſpleaſure whyche was perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted agaynſt the gloriouſe maieſtie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great god. But now who was able to make ſatiſfaction for ſo hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſe a diſpleaſure? Was there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye man vpon earthe able to do it? no not one. Was there any Angel in heauen able to do it? no not one no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for why ſhould any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:4959:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then man ſatiſfy or make ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des for mans fault?</p>
            <p>And it reſteth nowe that man is vtterly lyke to remayne oute of the fauouor of god and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently, to continue in the miſerable thraldu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deuell. But alas for ſorow to ſe how man is deſeruedly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the righteouſe iudgement of god which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtly gaynſay. Oh is there than no help? is ther no remedi? is ther no refuge? No ſurely: there is no refuge at all: vnles this onely ſhyft may be allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, that is to appeale from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere iuſtice of God, vnto his greate mercy, and to make an humble and an herty peticyon vnto hys grace to ſend his dere ſonne into the worlde to be incarnate and to become man to pay a full rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume vnto God for man to delyuer man out of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls captiuitie, to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyle, &amp; make
<pb facs="tcp:4959:24"/>
at one God and man, &amp; to offer him ſelfe vp for a pacifiynge Sacrifice vnto his father for mannes tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</p>
            <p>Whiche thing the vnſpeakeable mercye and the naturall kindnes of God beynge not required dyd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſeruedly graunt vnto man as he was yet hys very enemie and moſt diſobedient rebell.</p>
            <p>And thys was the ſole and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye raunſome that redemed Adam and all hys poſteritye oute of the greadye chawes of the olde Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente,<note place="margin">Al the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifiyng ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifices of Moſes la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we were but ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of chriſtes ſacrifice.</note> thys was the ſole and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye propiciatory ſacrifice that paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the yre of god, that wholy ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for mannes ſynnes, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red man againe into frendeſhip and fauour of God.</p>
            <p>And ſo all the Pacifiynge Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices that euer GOD inſtituted
<pb facs="tcp:4959:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and commaunded hys Seruaunte Moſes to publyſhe and ſette forthe to the Iſraelites or Iewes dyd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonelye ſignifye the ſayde Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>For after that the worlde had continued aboute two thouſande yeares wythout lawe, or any other preſcribed maner of liuynge, than nature it ſelfe dyd minyſter: at the laſte it pleaſed the hyghe maieſtie of God (that the mooe myghte be ſaued) to eſtablyſhe a lawe,<note place="margin">The b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Moſes lawe.</note> whiche ſhoulde as it were declare and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Lawe that was obſcurate, darckened, and farre degenerated by the ſiniſter corruption, which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niallye did iſſue from the fyrſte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Adam into all hys ofſprynge.</p>
            <p>Howebeit as God dyd not gyue thys lawe, vnto all Nations, but only to the Iewes beyng but a few
<pb facs="tcp:4959:25"/>
in numbre in compariſon of all the people in the worlde, ſo dyd not he forthwith open the miſteries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined therein, but ouer ſhadowed them with manifold ſacrifices, and diffuſe rites and ceremonies being ſignifications of good thynges to come.</p>
            <p>And moreouer as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wildernes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day time in a piller of a cloude to lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the waye, and the nyght tyme in a pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of fire to giue their corporal eies lyght, that they might iorney both day &amp; night toward the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe: ſo lykewyſe dyd the tender loue of God practiſe in furtheringe them to the very lande of promiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for he did ſo tempre hys traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which were neuer wont be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be grouerned by the light of anye morall lawe (and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:4959:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
groſſe, rude, and pore blind) might be traded vnder a clowdye and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall doctrine, but yet hauing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſparcles of his ſunny bright go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and ſo the eies of their mynde beyng nother vnmeaſurably dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor noſeled in blindnes, nor yet ouermuche daſeled and ouercome wyth the eyeing of ſhyning bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they mighte rather atchiue the ende of their ſpirituall progreſſe.</p>
            <p>And therfore all the ceremonies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in this law were none other thing,<note place="margin">The cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe</note> but introductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to lead vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſte.</p>
            <p>And all theſe fleſhe ſacrifices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokened the fleſhe ſacrifice of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodye, once offered vpon thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. But nowe to beate downe the Iewiſhe bulwark that the Popes ſouldiours haue round about their fortreſſe, we will recite certaine teſtimonies, as well out of
<pb facs="tcp:4959:26"/>
the olde teſtamente, as of the new, whyche ſhal euidently proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god delighteth not (though he required them for a time) in the externe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or the vtter offerynge of the ſacrifices commaunded by hym in Moſes hys lawe.<note place="margin">The abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of ſacrifice.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore he declared the ſame by the mouth of diuerſe of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, as it is written. Mala. i. I haue no pleaſure in you, ſayeth the Lorde of hoſtes: and as for youre meat offerynge. I wyll not accepte it at your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Again. Oſe v. They kyll ſacrifices bi heapes: and turne farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lorde, and I haue bene a rebuker of them all. And agayne. Prou. xv. The lorde abhorreth the ſacrifice of the vngodly. &amp;c. Item Eccle. xxxiiii. The hieſt doth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the giftes of the wicked. And God hath no delite in the offerings of the vngodly, nether may ſinne be
<pb facs="tcp:4959:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
reconſiled in the multitude of obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Who ſo bringeth an offering out of the goodes of the pore, doth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> killeth the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne before the fathers eyes. And in the .l. Pſal. I wil not reproue the (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord) bicauſe of thy ſacrifices, or for thy burnt offerings, bicauſe they were not alway before me. I wil take no bullock out of thy houſe: nor no he goates out of thy folde. For all the beaſtes of the foreſte are myne, and ſo are the cattell vpon a thouſande hylles. I knowe all the foules vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mountaynes: and the wild bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the feild are in my ſyght. If I be hungry, I wyl not tell the: for the whole worlde is mine, &amp; al that therin is. Thinkeſt thou that I wil eate Bulles fleſhe, and dryncke the bloude of goates?</p>
            <p>And in Ieremy .iii. Chapter you ſhal read, not of the abrogation of
<pb facs="tcp:4959:27"/>
Sacrifices onely, but alſo of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogation, &amp; diſanullynge of all the lawe,<note place="margin">The abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of the olde lawe.</note> and of the olde teſtamente w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. The texte goeth thys. When ye are increaſed and multiplied in the lande, than (ſaieth the Lorde) there ſhal no more boaſte be made of the arcke of the Lordes teſtament. No man ſhal thinke vpon it, nether ſhal anye man make mention of it: For from thence forth it ſhall neither be viſited nor honoured with giftes.</p>
            <p>Moreouer in the .xxxi. Chapter of the ſame prophete, you ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onely reade, of reſoluyng and repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the olde couenaunt or teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and the cauſe therof, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the ſubſtitution of the newe, &amp; of the deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nature, and tenure of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The new teſtament propheci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</note>And the words of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> text be theſe: Beholde, the daies wyll come (ſaith the Lorde) that I wil make a new
<pb facs="tcp:4959:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
couenaunte with the houſe of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and wyth the houſe of Iudah: not after the couenaunte whyche I made wyth their fathers, whan I toke them by the hande, and ledde them oute of the lande of Egypte, whiche couenaunt they brake: Yea euen whan I as an huſbande had rule ouer them, ſayeth the Lorde.</p>
            <p>But thys ſhall be the couenaunte that I wyl make with the houſe of Iſraell after thoſe dayes, ſayth the Lorde. I wyll plante my lawe in the inner part of them, and write it in theyr hertes, &amp; wyl be theyr god, and they ſhal be my people, &amp; from thence forth, ſhall no man teach his neighbour or his brother, and ſaye: knowe the Lorde, but they ſhall all knowe me, from the loweſte to the hyeſte, ſayth the Lorde. For I wyl forgiue their miſdedes, and wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre their ſinnes any more.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:28"/>Theſe teſtimonies (I thyncke) ſhall eaſilye perſwade euerye true chriſtian (whyche hath not a verye Iewyſhe herte) to be certified that as wel the carnall gratifiyng ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices required in Moſes lawe, be as vtterli determined, and as clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aboliſhed, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other pacifiynge ſacrifices, whom mooſte ſpeciallye we treated of hytherto.</p>
            <p>And if the gunne ſhote of theſe olde culuerynge pieces and double Cannons haue not ſufficientlye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen the bulworcke of the ſayde Popyſhe fortereſſe, we wyll yet ſhote of a piece or two of ſtrong newe ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Sacres and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: whereof we ſhall furnyſhe thys for one.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. viii ix.</note>The newe teſtamente weareth oute the olde: Nowe that whyche is worne out and waxed old, is rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy to vaniſhe awaye. For that firſt
<pb facs="tcp:4959:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
tabernacle verily had ordinaunces and ſeruynges of GOD and oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde holines. &amp;c. But into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde wente the hye Prieſte alone, once in the yere, not wythout bloud whyche he offered for him ſelfe, and for the ignoraunce of the people.</p>
            <p>Wherewyth the holye gooſte this ſignifieth, that the waye of holines was not yet opened, whyle as yet the fyrſte tabernacle was ſtanding. whyche was a ſimilitude for the tyme than preſente, in whych were offered giftes and Sacrifices, and coulde not make perfite (as pertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience) hym that dyd the gods ſeruice only with meates and drynckes, &amp; diuerſe waſhinges and iuſtifiynges of the fleſh, whych were ordeyned vnto the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Hebru. x.</note> For it is vnpoſſible that the bloude of Oxen and of Goates ſhoulde take awaye ſynnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:29"/>Wherfore wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he cometh into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the worlde, he ſayth. Sacrifice and offeringe thou wouldeſt not haue, but a body haſt thou ordeyned me. Burnte Sacrifices and ſynne offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes haſte thou not alowed. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd I, Lo I come: in the chiefeſte of the boke, it is written of me, that I ſhuld do thy wil, O God. Aboue whan he had ſayde. Sacrifice and offerynge, and burnt ſacrifices and ſynne offeryngs thou wouldeſt not haue, neither haſte alowed, whiche yet are offered after the lawe: than ſayde he: Lo, I come to do thy wyll O God. There taketh he away the fyrſte,<note place="margin">Al bodely ſacrifices ended in Chriſte.</note> to eſtablyſhe the later. In which wil we are ſanctified by the offeringe vp of the bodye of Ieſus Chriſte once for all.</p>
            <p>So than nowe, if it be a cleare caſe, and that by the playne textes of holy ſcripture, that ſynce Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4959:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
was once offred on the altare of the croſſe, al carnal ſacrifices and al ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of offerynges that euer were wont to be offered vpon the altares be wholy extinguiſhed, vtterli void and of none effect. And in as muche as no man (beynge in hys ryghte wytte, whan he aduiſedly percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and playnely vnderſtandeth that the cauſe of the fyrſte Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and buildynge of the Altares was for none other purpoſe,<note place="margin">That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continue with the ſacrifices</note> but to burne, or to offer ſacrifices or obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon, whyche maner of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices God wyl no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger accept) but he wil ſtraight wayes acknowlege that there ought not anye altare to remayne to any vſe among vs chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, after the death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our maiſter Chriſte: at which time as he proteſted hym ſelfe, ſayinge: Conſummatum eſt, it is finiſhed, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifiynge therby, that Moſes lawe
<pb facs="tcp:4959:30"/>
was not onely by hym preuented, fulfilled &amp; finiſhed: but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame lawe, or any commaundement, rite, ceremonie, or any other parte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteined (as concernynge anye burthening or iuriſdiction ouer the chriſtians) was to al intentes tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, taken away, and fully determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ended, and the goſpell as it were a newe lawe ſurrogated, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, &amp; eſtabliſhed in ſteade of the old.<note place="margin">The tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iers.</note> You ſe how the temporal law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers can tell on their fingers endes whyche is the aunciente commune lawe of the Realme, whyche be the cuſtomes of olde boroughes, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and contries, whiche is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute law, and which not, what eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes be exſpired, what ſtatutes be mitigated, what repealed, &amp; what euiued. Or what ſtatutes continue but from parliament to parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:4959:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and what ſtatute expoundeth an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea or what braunches of any ſtatute is cut away by the vygoure and egged force of an other ſtatute: Howe many do agre and concurre in one thynge, and howe manye be contrary one to an other.</p>
            <p>They know farther (euen as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilye as their Pater noſter) all the boke caſes that remaine in writing the yere of the raygne of the kinge, and the Terme alſo, and the better opinion of the Iudges, and what caſe ruled and what not.</p>
            <p>And I know wel that ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge requireth as greate, as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente, and as induſtrious a ſtudie, as for to be perfect in the bible and al the good writers and expoſiters thereof.</p>
            <p>Yet you, who glorye to be called by the name and title of doctours
<pb facs="tcp:4959:31"/>
of diuinitie, or bachiler of diuinitie, and profeſſe the exacte knoweledge thereof,<note place="margin">The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines.</note> are not (as it ſemeth by the confuſe hotchepotte that you haue made of your learnynge) ſo perfite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſene in your ſcience, as they in theyrs. And yet their ignoraunce is more excuſable than yours, &amp; their Practiſe more tollerable alſo than yours, for their ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: ſhal onli preiudice or endomag a man of his worldely goodes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite him of his earthly landes, or loſſe of hys body, which is nothing in compariſon of the ſoule, whome your ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and prepoſterous practice ſhall diſinherite of the land of promiſe, which is the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>But ſhall wee be foliſhe, groſſe, and vnapte in ſpiritual feates, and in thynges longynge to the Soule, and only wiſe and circumſpect, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityke
<pb facs="tcp:4959:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and fitte in al worldely mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whyche appertayne to bodily affayres?<note place="margin">That the lerned pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes be more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcrete &amp; folyſh, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple people.</note> Or ſhall the learned be more fonde than the vnlearned? or doeth muche learnynge make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> madde or doultiſhe? For what huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (be he neuer ſo ſimple) wil be about to plow his land wyth a whelebarowe, to harrowe it wyth a ſlede, or to carye with an harow? What huſbandman, I ſay is ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, as to go aboute to wede hys corne with a ſithe, to mowe his hey wyth a wedinge hoke, and to tedde the ſame with a rake? Is a leaden ceſterne made for to ſayle on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea? is a ſhyp made to be drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as a waggen vpon the land? do noble men build ſumptuous pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for their horſes to ſtand in, and lye them ſelues in olde ruinous ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles? or do men ordain fetherbeds for their dogges, and lye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:4959:32"/>
in kennellis? Who maketh a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar of an Oue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or an Oue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat? Or who maketh a threſhynge flore in hys dwellyng houſe, and a herth in hys barne? Who can make a pleaſaunte and a ſoote ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ketyng houſe, of fylthy Schamebles or of a ſtynking Slaughter houſe?</p>
            <p>Yea or who had not rather haue hys ſupper layed on a fayre Table before hym than on a bloudy But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chars Cradle?</p>
            <p>And ſo lyke wyſe (to apply ſome of theſe ſtraing Anagogies &amp; darke ſaynges to oure purpoſe) is not a Garnar more mete to lay vp grain in, than an Ouen? Is it not more mete to make a threſhynge flore in a barne than in a mans dwellynge houſe? And to make an herth to ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle fyre on in the myddes of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s houſe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mowes ſyde in hys barn? And ſo who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es
<pb facs="tcp:4959:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
olde ſlaughter Synagoge to ſerue for the newe Euangelyke banket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge. Temple? Or who had rather eaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ket of the Lordis Supper on a Iewiſh, a heathelyk or a Popyſh altare: then on a decent and a fayre comly Table?</p>
            <p>The vnbeleuynge Iewe defiyth Chriſtes Table and his ſupper al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. The vnfaythfull heathen thynke ſcorne of the ſame. The pope &amp; his papiſts make of it a god or a popet</p>
            <p>The Iew abhorryth vtterly our Religion. The Heathen in no ſauce can awaye wyth it.</p>
            <p>The Pope is well contented to be called a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The pope diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth.</note> yea to be thoght to be Chriſt him ſelf, ſo that ye geue hym leaue to lyue lyke a Iewe or an Heathen. And ſhall we ſeke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Shal we be partakers of their damnable Ceremonies, of theyr ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecrable Rites, and curſed Vſages?
<pb facs="tcp:4959:33"/>
Or is Chriſtes religion ſo vnperfit of it ſelfe, ſo neady &amp; beggerly that it muſte borowe imbring faſtes of the Heathen, borowe altares of the Pope, and borowe veſtimentes of the Iewes? beſide an vnnumerable ſorte of other like baggage,<note place="margin">Wedes in our religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note> whych hath bene weded nowe of late oute of Chriſtes religion, and now reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red home to the owners therof.</p>
            <p>Therefore lette vs either render home againe vnto the Heathen, the ſuperſticion of the imbrynge daies and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope his halowed altares and vnto the Iewes,<note place="margin">Exo. xxix.</note> their Aarons veſtimentes: or els let vs like good Companions ioyne togyther in a league wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked proui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye.</note> and be tenauntes in commune, and put oure religion wyth theirs in hotche potche, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawiers vulgar terme Qui primum happat primum cappat. And by my fey that peraduenture
<pb facs="tcp:4959:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were greate wiſedome: for ſo dyd oure fathers &amp; anceſters: and were it not good felowſhip to do as they did? Yea were it not good policy to holde on the bigger ſide? And are not more in numbre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtes Heathens and Iewes than of the Chriſtians? yea no doubte, thriſe ſo many at the leaſte: why then let vs be of one religion with them, &amp; they wyll take vs as their frendes, and we lykewyſe wyl take their parte. And ſo, we beyng than ſo many in numbre, and gathered togither and rayed in a puiſaunt and a myghtye army, ſhall ruſhe into heauen, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God &amp; hys angels wyll or no. And if all fayle, after that wee haue made mery by the waye, in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Popes purgatorye, we wyl march forward and come to the large and wyde kyngedome of the Prynce of thys worlde, euen
<pb facs="tcp:4959:34"/>
the myghty prynce Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth no man) and there ſhall wee be ſo curteſly enterteyned, ſo choiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cheriſhed, and ſo muche made of, as though we were his owne dere chyldren. For he loueth them alyfe whoe be at defiaunce wyth Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for theyr ſouerayne. Nowe as ye haue heard the fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſticall aduiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; brayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les councell of mans naturall wyt, (who perceyueth not the thynges that belong to the ſpirite of god) ſo herken what the ſpirit of god ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by the mouth of hys choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſel,<note place="margin">ſ. Cor. ii.</note> ſ. Paule, euen by theſe wordes.</p>
            <p>Dearlye beloued, fle from wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippinge of idoles.<note place="margin">ſ. Cor. x</note> I ſpeake vnto them that haue diſcretion, iudge ye what I ſay. The cuppe of thankes geuynge, wherwyth ye gyue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, is it not the partakynge of the bloude of Chriſte? The breade that
<pb facs="tcp:4959:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
we breake, is it not the partakinge of the body of Chriſte? For we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge manye are one breade and one bodye, in as muche as we are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of one breade. Beholde Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell after the fleſhe. They that eate ſacrifices, are thei not partakers of the altare? What ſhall I nowe ſay then? Shall I ſay that the idole is any thynge? Or that whyche is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto the idole is anye thyng? Naye. But thys I ſaye, that loke what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hethen offer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offer thei to deuils &amp; not to god. Ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not drink of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup of the lord, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuils. Now wold I not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhuld be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felowſhip w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deuils, Ye can not be partaker of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes table, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuils? Or will ye prouoke the lord? Are we ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he? I may do al thinges, but al things are not expedient. I may do al thyngs, but all thynges edifye not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:35"/>Nowe I truſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as many of vs as haue receyued the ſpirite of God ſhall ſone perceyue by the meanyng of the texte nowe before rehearſed, that the chriſtians in no wyſe maye be partakers with the Heathens or Iewes in idoles, altares, ſacrifices offerynges, or ſuche other vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenlyke ceremonies.</p>
            <p>For (as the ſame Apoſtle ſayth) what felowſhyp hath ryghtuouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnrightuouſenes?<note place="margin">ii. Cor. vi</note> what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hath lyght wyth darckenes? howe agrreeth Chriſt and Belial? or what parte hathe the beleuer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vnbeleuer? howe accordeth the temple of god wyth images? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But nowe I praye you, do you not ſee wyth what a care, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what a diligence, and wyth what an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte affection the holye Apoſtle of Chriſte exhorteth,<note place="margin">The gret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iligence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f ſaynte</note> counceleth, and calleth vpon the chriſtians, leſt they
<pb facs="tcp:4959:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhoulde kepe company or be yoked wyth the Heathen or the Iewes,<note place="margin">Paule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtes religion ſhold not be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled.</note> or leſte they ſhould admit and receyue anye of theyr ſuperſticious rites, or wycked ceremonies, and myngle the ſame wyth Chriſtes religion?</p>
            <p>Yea, &amp; the Apoſtles dyd ſo much abhorre, eſchew and feare, leſt ſuch confuſe mingle mangle of ſtraunge ſuperſticions (whether they were of the Heathens vayne rites, or of the Iewes lawe) in ſo muche that they bade not onely farewell to all the ceremoniall and Iudicial lawe of Moſes, but alſo (bycauſe they woulde differ frome the Iewes in keping holyday) they tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated and chaunged the celebration of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both from Saturdaye to So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day. For the ſeuenth day wherupon by one of hys ten commaundementes God commaunded vs to reſt, was on Saturday, and not on So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day.
<pb facs="tcp:4959:36"/>
The lyke affection and mynde was Conſtantine the Emperour of (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrynge the memorial of the vaine Heathens Goddes) whan he ſued vnto one Silueſter the fyrſte, By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of Rome, that it myghte be decreed, that the dayes of the weke whyche had before the names and tytles of the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne,<note place="margin">The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies in the weke bi a decre altered.</note> Mone, Mars, Mercury, Iupiter, Venus, &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, ſhoulde be called the fyrſt fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, the ſecond ferye, the thyrde fery, the fourthe, the fyfte, the ſyxte, the ſeuenth: in lyke maner as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes counted theyr dayes from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daye.</p>
            <p>But it pleaſed hym that the firſt fery myght be called Dies Dominicꝰ alſo, whyche we name Sondaye, and that Saturday ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sabatum, of the olde holydaye and reſte of the Hebrues.</p>
            <p>And if ſuche vigilante circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection
<pb facs="tcp:4959:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and carefull mynde to flee from hauynge any mutual conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation (as wel in wordes as in thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Iewes &amp; other infidels had ſtyll continued in chriſten men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hertes euer ſince the Apoſtles tyme hytherto:<note place="margin">Maiſter Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, holpe the Pope to ſet vp his alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> than neded no man to trauayle at thys preſente daye to wryte or inueyghe againſte the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſte intruſion of altares.</p>
            <p>But well worthe the tyme of the olde prymatiue church, whan eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye thynge (as Polidorus Vergili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us recordeth) in the adminiſtration of the Lordes ſupper was playne,<note place="margin">☜</note> ſyncere, and wythoute any minling of ceremonies, contaynynge more vertue than ſolemnitie.</p>
            <p>Herken than to thys teſtimonye (al ye Papiſtes) and giue good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite vnto it, (for he that fyrſt wrote it) is the Pope his owne countrey manne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:37"/>For ſurely he ſpeaketh herein as trulye as dyd the biſhop Cayphas whan he affirmed that it was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that one man ſhould dye for the people, than all the people ſhoulde peryſhe.</p>
            <p>But woulde God it had pleaſed hys holye Spirite to ſpeake by the mouth of the pope, as he hath done bi the mouth of Balaam, Cayphas and of other as euyll menne. Than ſhoulde not all the people haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, but rather one manne. And would God I ſaye, that thys Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidorie of Polidorus had ben more liberally beſtowed on the common people in Englande. Than would they more frelye and wyth a better wyll obeye and imbrace the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical proceadynges of the hygher powers. And ſeynge than that of a verye trueth (accordinge to the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Polidorus) the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of Chriſte was repleniſhed wyth more vnfeyned holines, and garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed wyth manye mooe godly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, before it knewe any thynge of theſe newe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſolemne ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and holylyke traditions.</p>
            <p>What the deuill than was it, that put into the Popes braynes, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer charge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion wyth ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye folde vayne ceremonies, and ſo diuerſe pernitious traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? it was but euen the ſame deuill that ſette a worcke Mahometh the notorious falſe prophete to play the like part. Yea it was the ſelfe ſame blynd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll that maketh euen at thys daye all the Papiſtes and the Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſtes to adhere &amp; ſtycke to their falſe goddes the Popes and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamethes diſceitful lawes &amp; vaine traditions, more than to the Lorde Chriſt, and hys healthſome goſpel.</p>
            <p>But nowe to let paſſe theſe two
<pb facs="tcp:4959:38"/>
greate vſurpers of Chriſtes digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and moſte hyghe power, and to let them ſyncke in theyr owne ſinne and to talk no more of them but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtyckinge ſtedfaſte to our tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge to defende oure ſelues frome the dartes whom we ſe already di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and ſhaken agaynſte vs by oure aduerſaryes the poyſonfull Papyſtes.</p>
            <p>Howe be it bycauſe my chiefeſt entente is, to wryte thys treactyſe for them that be vnlearned, I wyl fyrſte open and declare ſomewhat of the nature of one terme lately bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of the Latines, and therfore not ſo well knowne of euerye En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe Reader: whyche terme per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture I ſhall haue occaſion to vſe nowe and than, ere I ſhal haue done wyth this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o allude</note>The terme is to Allude. And a manne doeth allude, whan he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:4959:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that whyche hath a priuye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte or reſemblaunce to an other thynge: as ſomtime a man alludeth to a worde as thus.</p>
            <p>The good mome is fole a towne, meanynge that the good manne is forthe of the towne. Here the allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is in mome and foole, for man and forth. Sometyme a man allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to a practice or a dede doynge, as when I ſaye: Let me alone with hym for I wyll walke hym, I wyll dreſſe hym lyke a Lennarde, I will make Stockefiſhe of hym. &amp;c. And ſometime a man alludeth to an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory as thus.</p>
            <p>By lyke oure Kynge (God ſaue hys grace) after his fathers depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, dyd aſke of GOD in hys prayer Wyſedome, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng &amp; not long lyfe, neither riches neither reuengment on his enimies
<pb facs="tcp:4959:39"/>
ſeynge the Lord hath ſo endued his herte wyth ſuche vnſpeakable wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng &amp;c. and hys maieſtie wyth ſuch ryches and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Nowe in ſo ſayinge the alluſion is had vnto the hiſtory of Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iii. Reg. iii. And ſo at the laſte to re: turne frome alludyng to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng.</p>
            <p>Where ſoeuer therfore, ye do read in the newe teſtament of thys word altare: if ye marke it well and circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, ye ſhall clearly perceiue that the vſe therof is not ther awhyt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newyd or confirmyd, but by ſome occaſion ſpoken of, and rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, ended, and adnulled.</p>
            <p>As in the .v. of Math. The text I wyll not reherſe now, becauſe it is here once before reherſed, the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wherof (though in many wordes) is not farre diſagreable from this.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> place of Math. expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</note>You Iewes, ſayth Chriſt, which
<pb facs="tcp:4959:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
receyued a Lawe of my Father by the miniſterie of Moſes: by whych Lawe ye were commaunded to vſe certaine outwade ceremonies, as it wer to enure your ſelfes in a religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and that it ſhoulde appeare to all nations, that you were my fathers owne peculiar People.</p>
            <p>And ye were alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyd by the ſame Lawe, that when ſo euer you ſhuld tranſgreſſe or breake the ſame or any Article therof: that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhoulde offer vp Sacrifices or Offeryngs vnto my Father where ye myght be blameleſſe, holden ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and be acquited by the ſame lawe, al youre former treſpaces &amp; ſynnes notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, and rather iuſtified before the worlde, than in the preſence of God.</p>
            <p>But ſence ye haue altogether ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed the ſayed ſacrifices, chewynge the Barcke therof, and groſſely fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:4959:40"/>
on the vtter parte of it, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge no fode of the inner pyth, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haueynge any regarde to thoſe thynges which were chiefly ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame ſacrifices: my father hath warned alredy by the mouthe of hys Prophetes, that he paſſethe nought of your ſacrifices and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynges that you offer vnto hym on Altares (whiche were but tokyns of inwarde holynes) but the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and offerynges whych he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and pleaſed wythe al, are theſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. ii.</note> a ſtomake broken with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and a herte ſmytten &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſorow,<note place="margin">Oſe. vi.</note> and to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie one to an other. And if ye wil of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp theſe, my Father ſhall neuer deſpiſe them. Therfore thou Iewe wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer thou brekeſt ani of the x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as whan thou kylleſt anye man, other by thought or dede: whan thou arte angrye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thy brother by hys faulte or miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, or els whan thou haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him occaſion (by reuilyng, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng or callyng hym knaue or other wiſe by vſeyng or practiſeyng anye diſpytfull worde or dede towardes hym) to be moued to wrath and to be diſpleaſed wyth the.</p>
            <p>Than if thou wylt pacifye the wrath and Indignation of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Iniurie and diſpleaſur that thou haſt don to hys ſeruaunt: verilye I tell the it auayleth the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng at all, to come and offer any maner of bodily ſacrifices or obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the altare: yea &amp; though thou be come nere vnto the altare and thy gyft wyth the, euen redy to be offered (if it chaunce the than to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre any maner of diſpleaſure betwixt the and thy brother) thou muſt not, I ſaye, offer vp thy gyfte immediatly (as though thy offeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:4959:41"/>
ſhould rather pacifie &amp; more pleaſe my father than brotherly loue and concorde) thou muſte not I ſay go that way to worke: but thou muſt leaue thy gifte (as a thynge nought worthe of it ſelfe) before the altare: and than go thy way to ſatiſfye thy brother, to pleaſe thy brother, and to reconcile the to thy brother. And whan thou haſt after this ſort plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſeruaunt, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maiſt thou the bolder approch to the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the maiſter:<note place="margin">ſ. Ioh. iii</note> and than if thou wilt nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des offer vp thy gyfte, he wyll ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accepte it, and take it in good worthe.</p>
            <p>Nowe haue you heard howe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Chriſte doeth attribute vnto ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and offerynges, for whoſe vſe altares are ordeined, and onelye ſerue. For ye muſte ſpeciallye note thys, that Chriſte in thys place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded &amp; opened vnto the Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:4959:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
moſte chyeflye, the true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and meanynge of their lawe wyth the ryghte vſe of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereof.</p>
            <p>For it fared than wyth theim as it dyd wyth me, whan I was a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Papiſte, at what tyme I was at thys poynte wyth god. That if I had hearde maſſe boeth ſondaye and holye day,<note place="margin">The chie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> had ſayde our Lady mattens, or our ladyes pſalter, kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and lycked deuoutly ſaintes fete (for ſo called thei their images) and beſprynkeled my ſelfe well fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redlye wyth coniured water, &amp; had done the ſuperſticious penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to me by my gooſtly, ſhall I ſaye enemye or father? Than I ſay was I at ſuch poynte wyth God, I thought it, and aſſuredly beleued that I had done my full dutie vnto hym, thoughe I neuer once called to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the benefite of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes
<pb facs="tcp:4959:42"/>
death, as wel in ſatiſfiyng and pacifiynge for all the treſpaces and ſynnes of my former euill life, and naughty conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Yea beſides all thys popyſh and deuilliſhe preſumption, I thought farther, that if I had done the ſaide vayne workes &amp; ſuch other no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a Papiſte.</note> that I was no more beholden vnto god tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was to me; neither gaue I him more thankes for par, donyng me of my ſynnes: than one marchaunt man geueth to another for the optaynynge a peny worthe for a penie.</p>
            <p>But thankes be vnto the Lorde who of hys mere clemency, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me out of thys blynde popyſhe hereſye, and vouchſafe of hys lyke goodnes to worcke the ſemblable myracle in as manye as yet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſuche damnable errour.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>But nowe againe to come to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And as I was thus tangeled, and abhominablye deceyued, and trayned, and brought vp in tender age, in the Popes holilyke Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before Chriſtes ſeconde byrthe here in Englande, euen ſo were the Iewes before hys fyrſte byrthe in Iudea wonderouſly deceyued, and ſhamefully ſeduced and that by the fayned newe Doctryne that their Popes I meane theyr ſcribes and Phariſes hadde brought into their churche.</p>
            <p>And for to roote that doctryne oute of the Iewes lawe, was the occaſion of Chriſtes Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſayde place of Mathew.</p>
            <p>So lykewyſe in the .xxiii. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſame Euangeliſte he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth the Iewes for to dooe all thynges bothe greate or ſmall that
<pb facs="tcp:4959:43"/>
the Scribes and Phariſeis prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto them, as long as thei tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not oute of Moſes chayre, nor ſwarue not from teachyng the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere &amp; pure lawe of Moſes. There amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other matters he doth ſharp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly condemne theyr blynd doctours for a certaine conſtitucion that they had made, beynge ledde wyth aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice or couetuouſenes: The ſumme and effecte of whyche conſtitution whych they had made be conteined in theſe fewe wordes.</p>
            <p>Who ſo euer ſwereth bi the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that is nothynge: but who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſwereth by the gold of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he is bounde by hys othe. And who ſo euer ſwereth by the Altare that is nothynge, but who ſo euer ſwereth by the offerynge that is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the altare, he is bounde by hys Othe.</p>
            <p>Thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution of theirs doth
<pb facs="tcp:4959:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Chriſte confute wyth naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon callyng them foles and wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous blynde, that they woulde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute ſo groſſe, and ſo farre frome reaſon, a tradition as this is.</p>
            <p>But I thynke that Chriſte wyll neuer ſay to the Pope for hys fine Canons, decrees, and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (though they were made for the like purpoſe) as he dyd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcribes and phariſeis: But I wyll not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake that he wyll not (as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Herode) ſaye vnto hym on thys wyſe. Thou wyly Fox, why dideſt thou looſe that, whyche I bounde? or why dideſte thou bynde what I dyd looſe?</p>
            <p>Nowe I praye the gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der do not blame me for this ſhort digreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather the fox, whoſe craftye wiles cauſed the ſame. And thus from Pope to Papiſte. Thou Papiſt, euen thou that of late wold<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt
<pb facs="tcp:4959:44"/>
defend thyne altare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this text and ſo thou mayſte in dede if thou wilt ſubdue thy necke vnto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie yoke of Moſes his lawe, vnder which law al thoſe people wer ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt preached as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd. And if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to lyue vnder the lawe of Moſes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath Chriſte dyed in vayne for the: and therefore gette the hence vnto the Iewes, whyche ſtyll loke for a worldely Chriſte to come.</p>
            <p>But thou good Papiſt that art wyllynge to renounce thy Poperye and to receyue Chriſtianitye, thou muſte conſider, that where ſo euer Chriſte doeth inculcate the lawe of Moſes vnto his contrey men after the fleſh (I meane the Iewes) that he doeth it chieflye to thys entente, that they ſhoulde wythdrawe their necks from the vntollerable yocke and heauy burthen of the lawe and
<pb facs="tcp:4959:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
receyue the eaſy yocke and the lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> burthen of his moſt bleſſed goſpel.</p>
            <p>For the lawe,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohn. i</note> as Saynct Iohn ſayeth, was geuen by Moſes, but grace and trueth came by Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Euerye good chriſtian therefore muſte marcke thys alſo. That the merciful lord Ieſus Chriſte (whoſe nature and propertye was not to ſtriue nor to breake a broſed rede) thoughe the ſtrength and vygoure of the law and prophetes extended no lenger but to the tyme of Iohn the Baptiſte as Chriſte hym ſelfe dyd ſignifye the ſame vnto theym, and declarynge that the kingdome of heauen being the Goſpel ſuccea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and was at hande euen before hys paſſion: yet dyd he rather per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte or ſomewhat derogate than vtterly abrogate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of Moſes
<pb facs="tcp:4959:45"/>
vntyll ſuch tyme as he thorowe his bloude and Death ſealed vppe and ſtablyſhed hys newe Teſtamente, whych then immediatly dyd wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the olde. Therefore euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is as prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as the Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fyrſte (all the circumſtancis beyng wel perpenſed) wyll be ware to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue euery ſentence and euery word wrytten in the newe Teſtament as parte therof, or confirmyd by the ſame: as where Chriſte declareth the Lawe &amp;c. or where Chriſte in the ſame .xxiii. cha. ſpeaketh of an altare menyng nothing leſſe then to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme or renewe the vſe of altars emonge hys chriſtians but all togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to vpbrayde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedyng theyr wicked au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſters cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elnes in kyllyng of Prophetis.</p>
            <p>Here hys owne wordes are theſe. Beholde I ſende you Prophetis &amp; Wiſe men, and Scribes and ſome
<pb facs="tcp:4959:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal kyll and crucifie and ſome of them ſhall you ſcourge in your Synnagoges, and perſecute them frome Citie to Citie: that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you maye come all the ryghtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe bloude, whyche hath ben ſhed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, from the bloud of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe Abell, vnto the bloud of za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ſonne of Barachias whome ye ſlewe bitwene the Temple and the altare &amp;c. But ful lyttle (god kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth) wotteth he what an Altare meanith that wol alledg thys place for an altare.</p>
            <p>And euen of lyke force be the .ii. places before reherſed, in the bigin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of the boke, on the papiſtes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, whych places were chopped out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt cha. of .ſ. Luks goſpel &amp; of the .xvii. of his boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> actes. But I can not denay but one might gather thereof ſuche an argumente as this. The Iewes had theyr al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares,
<pb facs="tcp:4959:46"/>
and the Heathen had theyr al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tares, Ergo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt haue altares. But either I am a ſimple Logician or els the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wolde better frame, and a more true conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent folowe after thys ſorte. The Iewes had altares, &amp; the Heathen had altares alſo, ergo the Pope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng a participle muſt haue halteres lykewiſe. But I promes you there be two places, one .i. Cor. ix. &amp; the other, Heb. xiii. whych myght hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not ſomewhat trauailed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures to thincke verili y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alters be there ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of as things apertaining to vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hold of Chriſtes newe Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where it is nothynge ſo. For the texte to the Corh. hath thus. <hi>An neſcitis quoniam qui in ſacrario opera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, que de ſacrario ſunt edunt? Et qui in altario deſeruiunt, cum altario participant? Ita et Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ordinauit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is qui Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelium anu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, de Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelio viuere.</hi> Wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greke
<pb facs="tcp:4959:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
texte for Altario hath <hi>Thyſiaſterion,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>Sacrarium</hi> a place for holy thynges, as wel as Altariſt an altare. But to make no moe wordes than nede:<note place="margin">Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel.</note> all the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of .ſ. Paul in thys place tendeth to proue that they wych preach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, oughte of duitie to haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t liuyng therby. And to perſwad the Corhinth. therto: he vſeth thys Induction. Whye, you Corhinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, do you not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre howe you your ſelfes before ye had receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachyng of Chriſtes goſpell, dyd fynd ſuch as miniſtered in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the Idoles? And do you not ſe emonge the Iewes alſo howe the prieſtes &amp; the Leuites which wait on the altare, haue the offrings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toward their ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and liuing? And why ſhould not he likewiſe that taketh pains to preach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell haue a liuing alſo?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:47"/>The authour of the goſpell wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ordeyned that the true go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpellers ſhoulde haue a liuynge: yet had I rather vſe greate ſcarcitie, &amp; worcke wyth myne owne handes, than to be onerous and chargeable vnto you.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles if ye denay a liuyng to an other that ſhall require it of you, if he preache the Goſpell vnto you, ye muſt nedes be adiudged to contemne and ſet nought by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wordes that are preached vnto you, and euen deſpiſe the authoure thereof, whiche is the Lord Ieſus Chriſte. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And. S. Thomas and Remigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us (as we haue nowe declared this place accordynge to their mind) do thynke that Sacrarium here hathe a relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the idoles of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and Altarium vnto the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Iewes. Now therfore
<pb facs="tcp:4959:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
who ſo deliteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathens deuil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſhe idolatry, or Iewiſh ſacrifices he maye well inoughe wreſte thys place to maintane his altares: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing I had leuer he dyd tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I. But nowe or we ſet vpon to bater, and beate downe the heade corner ſtone of their Popiſhe Botereulx: we wyl fyrſt declare yet one gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer terme mooe, for the vnlearned ſake, whyche thoughe it be no hygh point of diuinitie, neuertheles who ſo hath not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege therof, hys diuinitie is but humaniti, or rather carnalitie, than true knowledge in diuine matters.</p>
            <p>And ſo the grammarians cal it a ſpeach ſpoken by a fygure called Metonimya, whan the thynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned is mente by the name of the thyng that contayneth it.<note place="margin">Metony<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mia or d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> As whan wee ſaye, reache hyther the cuppe: meanynge to haue the dryncke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned
<pb facs="tcp:4959:48"/>
in the cuppe. Thys figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue ſpeache vſed Chriſte him ſelfe whan he ſaide.<note place="margin">Luk. xxii.</note> Thys cuppe is the new teſtament in my bloud. Wher he ment of the wine, and not of the cuppe. And likewiſe Mathew .xxiii where he ſpeaketh by the name of the City vnto them that dwelled in the citie, ſayinge: Ieruſalem Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, thou that ſlayeſt the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. &amp;c. Suche maner of ſpeache is alſo muche vſed in the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. As Eſai. i. Heare O heauen and herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> O earth. And in an other place. Howle ye ſhips of Tharſis.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Papiſtes muſt eyther graunt that, that kind of ſpeache is vſed in the text, that we ſhall anone rehearſe hereafter, or els muſt they graunt that the Iewes (whoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares or rather Sacrifices and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydden meate, the writer of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle alludeth vnto) were wonte to
<pb facs="tcp:4959:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
eate vp theyr altares beynge made of ſtones or of other metall harder tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtones. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wer hard meat in dede. Yea that were meate alone for Oſtriches? Yea or rather ſtone mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te were more mete for ſuch as haue ſtony hertes,<note place="margin">Oſtriche is a beaſt that ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth gaddes of ſtele &amp; digeſteth them.</note> as haue al Papiſticall Doctours who againſte their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, knoweledge, and learnynge, and beynge all deſtitute of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God, cry and ſhoute for the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their welbeloued altares, <hi>Habemus altare, Habemus altare, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus altare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea and I maye tell you thys <hi>Habemus altare,</hi> is their iudgelynge ſticke, whereby they dooe Iuggle vnto the vnlearned, it is al their hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and onely refuge agaynſte all tempeſtes, and this is as well their ſhote anker as their halow at their hoyſinge vp of their ankore.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:49"/>But to hale in my ſaile and to la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the propoſed haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The engliſh texte of <hi>Habemus altare</hi> written. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue .xiii. is thys: Be not caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute wyth diuerſe &amp; ſtraung lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges: for it is a good thinge that the herte be ſtabliſhed wyth grace, and not wyth meates, which haue not profited them that haue hadde their paſtyme in them.</p>
            <p>We haue an altare, of the which they haue no power to eate, which ſerue in the tabernacle. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here he dothe in a maner make a bryefe rehearſal of all the chiefeſt maters that he entreated of before, addynge thereto diuerſe godly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to perſwade the Hebrues to abyde in thys learnynge: Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynge them alſo, by alludynge vnto theyr lawe beynge but a ſhadowe to cleaue vnto the goſpell, and to let go y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadow. And therfore he ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:4959:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thus vnto them. And as you hadde certayne Sacrifices offered on the altares whereof it was not lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful euen for the very offerers to eat: ſo lykewyſe haue wee a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice once offered vpon the altare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, wherof it is not lawfull for as many of you as be yet duſkened wyth the ſhaddowe of the lawe to eate, nor to be patakers of it at al.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore muſte the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes be thought not only to be of to childyſhe a wytte and of no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge, but rather furiouſe and mad, if they continue to proue their ſtony altares by thys text.</p>
            <p>And therefore woulde I thinke it an exceadyng good dede for ſuch as inioye their ryght wytte, to pick out from amongeſt them ſelues as manye as are vexed wyth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of the ſayde kynde of phreneſy, and ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them to Bedlem, or to their
<pb facs="tcp:4959:50"/>
owne citye of Rome. For els they ſhall ſtyll infect other, and do more hurte then euery man is ware of.</p>
            <p>At the laſte to drawe toward an ende in thys matter. Where thys worde altare is read in the .vi. viii. and .xi. Chapters of the reuelation of ſaint Iohn: if altare in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, admittynge the lyke trope and figuratiue ſpeache, do not ſignifye Chriſte alſo (God knoweth) it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth nothynge leſſe than the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of ſuche Altares as the Pope hathe fylled euerye corner of Chriſtes churche wythall.</p>
            <p>And if the Papyſtes (after that all the teſtimonies, as wel of thold and the new teſtament haue fayled them) go aboute to wreſte the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of the old doctours, for the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhyng of their altares, they ſhal get nothynge therby, but ſtyl vtter
<pb facs="tcp:4959:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their owne groſſe ignoraunce, or theyr peruerſe blyndnes. For wher ſo euer thold catholyke doctours, vſed thys worde altare for the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Table, than alluded they vnto the Iewes altare and mente there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the croſſe whyche ſerued as an altare to offer vpon the ſacrifice of Chriſtes naturall bodye.</p>
            <p>And forſoth, ye Papiſtical prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, as many of you as vnderſtode the Latine, and marked what you reade (and if ye hadde bene Bees,<note place="margin">The Bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth honi on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame flour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Spider gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> and not Spiders) you might haue gathered the nature of thys maner of alluſion or reſemblau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes croſſe vnto the Altares of the Iewes euen out of your own poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned maſſe.</p>
            <p>Whyche well myghte be called <hi>Maſſa, farrago, vel Chaos, quo ſacra pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phanis, miſcebat Papa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4959:51"/>Euen a very hotch pot, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych the Pope put al maner of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and al maner of rites &amp; ceremonies, both good &amp; bad, &amp; leſſons of holy ſcripture, and of vnholye ſcripture: thys hotch pot I ſaye ordeyned he, euen for hys deare children, &amp; catch who catche maye: happe good or badde: happe holye, happe vnholy, happe godlye, happe deuillyſhe.</p>
            <p>For do you not remembre howe ye mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled (howe ye redde I wold ſaye) in a certayne ryme of youre ſayde hotche potte whyche began. <hi>Laudes crucis extollamus, nos qui cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis crult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus. &amp;c. O qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quam pre clara, fuit hec ſalutis ara, rubens agni ſanguine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O howe excellent and howe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye, was thys Altare of tree, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprynckeled wyth Lambes bloud?</p>
            <p>And agayne in an other proſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ara crucis, lampas lucis, vera ſalus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum.</hi> Whoſe ſence in Englyſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4959:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
worde for worde is thys. The al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare of the cros, the lampe of light and the verye healthe of men.</p>
            <p>Nowe thoughe your owne time makers of youre Popyſhe ſeruyce haue vſed ſo manye Metaphories, ſo many tropes, and ſo manye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed ſpeches, vſurping one word for an other, vntyll at the laſte they ran on the rocke of vnexcuſable I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrye, and plaine ſuperſtition: you muſte not therefore thyncke that the holye Doctours ranne ſo headlynge in their worckes, that they abuſed any one terme of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes religion, wherbi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame might be a ſtomblinge blocke vnto anye, ſauynge vnto the chyldrene of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who continuallie ſtumble at the verye worde of God.</p>
            <p>And to confeſſe the trueth, the old holy fathers and catholyke wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters no doubte are worthye much
<pb facs="tcp:4959:52"/>
commendation, for that thei great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traueyled in reuolutynge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundynge the ſacred Scriptures committyng to wryting theyr cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof: wyllynge and requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge that al their poſteritie ſhould gyue no farther credite thereto, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their cenſures and interpretations ſhoulde ſeme to be agreable vnto fayeth.</p>
            <p>Whoſe worthye antiquitie and graue authority notwythſtanding, wee yet neades muſte preferre and eſteme of more importau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue alſo that he is a greate deale of a more infallible and vndeceyua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgemente,<note place="margin">Act. ix. Galat. ii.</note> whome the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſte ſaynte Luke ſo to be, doeth beare wytneſſe vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And I meane none other, but euen oure Apoſtle Saynte Paule whoe calleth the borde where the
<pb facs="tcp:4959:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Spirituall feaſte of the Lordes Supper is celebrated and eaten v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, the table of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>O the depenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riches, both of the wyſedome and knoweledge of GOD, who ſo manye hundreth yeares paſſed, dyd fore ſee that hys moſte holye worde ne ſhoulde not be ſette to a fall,<note place="margin">Luke. ii.</note> but to an vpriſyng to all hys choſen people?</p>
            <p>And of thys place we maye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it pleaſed God to poure more aboundaunce of foreknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in hys Apoſtle Paules com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious doctrine, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the large writing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> notable learned doctor Saynt Auguſtine.</p>
            <p>For ſaynte Paule throughe the ſecrete aduertiſement of the holye Gooſte dyd knowe before hande, that if he hadde geuen the name of an Altare vnto the LORDE hys
<pb facs="tcp:4959:53"/>
Table, that there would be in time to come certayne Iewyſh teachers that woulde builde and ſette vppe Popyſhe altares in ſtede of tables to ſerue the Lordes ſupper vpon.</p>
            <p>And ſurely the holy doctor. ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne nor anye other godly wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter woulde neuer haue vſed thys terme altare ſo often after that ſort as they dyd, if they had hadde but the leaſte inckelynge in the worlde of foreknowlege what abſurditie, what inconuenience and what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and abhomination haue ben grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on their tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated termes.</p>
            <p>And I praye you what though ſainte Auguſtine or other doctours vſed to terme the lordes ſupper the Sacrament of the altare,<note place="margin">Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> altare.</note> whych if it be as I take it (I take it after the moſte ſounde and fayeth fulliſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge) the vnlearned people ſhoulde not be greatelye beholden
<pb facs="tcp:4959:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnto them for their ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge termes beyng ſo farre fetched. For thus I vnderſtand them.</p>
            <p>The Sacramente of the altare that is to ſaye: the ſygne of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, whyche altare betokeneth the croſſe, whych croſſe betokeneth the Sacrifice that was offered on the croſſe, or the paſſion and deathe of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Wherefore good Chriſten brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs that are homely felowes not be aſhamed of the olde termes that wee haue at oure home in the texte of holy ſcripture, whyche cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the reuerende and healthfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of the Lordes death by breakinge of bread,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x. i. Cor. xi.</note> by the name of the Lordes ſupper, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and partakynge of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and bloude of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>And the thynge wherat we<note n="‡" place="margin">Vel pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pter arto latriam vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dam tutius e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit vt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nu flecte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s menſe dominice populus accu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bere aſſueſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> ſit deuoutlye to eate the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb facs="tcp:4959:54"/>
lette vs boeth haue it, and call it the Lordes borde, or the Lordes table, and not a borowed towell, nor a Popyſhe ſtone altare, nor yet a wodden altare, with a Superhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. And lette vs Preſente wyth ſo far fetched termes and ſo deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye boughte, the Popes glace, and hys fayre Ladyes of Rome.</p>
            <p>Nowe bicauſe I truſte that we haue vaunquiſhed and geuen an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow to the chiefeſt part of the Popes ſouldiers, batered and bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten downe to the grounde the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Botereulx, and the greate ſtay of hys ſtronge holde &amp; Forteceſſe: therefore ſhall oure trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet blow a retreit in this battayle. Praiſed be the Lorde. Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:54"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ii. Cor. ii.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>¶Thanckes be vnto God whyche alwayes geueth vs the vyctorye in Chriſte, and opened the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of hys knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by vs in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place.</p>
                  <p>For we are vnto God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Chriſte, boeth amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are ſaued, &amp; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> periſh. To theſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauour of deth to deth: to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauour of life to life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4959:55"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Robert Crowley, dwellyng in Elye rentes in Holburne. The yere of our Lord. M.D.L.</p>
            <p>⚹ ☞ ⚜ ☜ ⚹</p>
            <p>❀ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ❀</p>
            <p>⚜</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>¶Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
